The Eastern Front is a war film directed by Rick Roberts.
A dwindling group of German soldiers battle to return to
their lines on the harsh Eastern Front.
Aliya, played by Mhairi Calvey.
German Officer, played by Chris Wilson.
Rosa Alexandrova, played by Laura Jean Marsh.
Aleksy, played by Justin Hayward.
Lieutenant Joachim Brandt, played by Tim Seyfert.
Private Theo Weiss, played by Josh Harper.
The Eastern Front, also known as the Great Patriotic War, or the German–Soviet War, was a theatre of World War II
fought between the European Axis powers and Allies, including the Soviet Union (USSR) and Poland.
It encompassed Central Europe, Eastern Europe, Northeast Europe (Baltics), and
Southeast Europe (Balkans), and lasted from 22 June 1941 to 9 May 1945.
Of the estimated 70–85 million deaths attributed to the war, around 30 million
occurred on the Eastern Front, including 9 million children.
The Eastern Front was decisive in determining the outcome in the European theatre of operations in
World War II and is the main cause of the defeat of Nazi Germany and the Axis nations.
Historian Geoffrey Roberts noted that "more than 80 percent of all combat
during the Second World War took place on the Eastern Front".
The Axis forces, led by Germany, invaded the Soviet Union
in Operation Barbarossa on 22 June 1941.
Despite warnings and the deployment of Axis armies on his borders, Stalin refused to believe that Hitler would
invade and forbade any defensive preparations as to not provoke possible German retaliation.
Thus, the Soviets were caught completely unprepared.
They were unable to halt deep Axis advances into
Russia, which came close to seizing Moscow.
However, the Axis offensive stalled and failed to capture the city, and Hitler
shifted his focus to the oil fields of the Caucasus the following year.
German forces advanced into the Caucasus under Fall Blau
("Case Blue"), launched on 28 June 1942.
The Soviets decisively defeated the Axis at the Battle of Stalingrad—the bloodiest battle in the war
and arguably in all of history—making it one of the key turning points of the front.
A second great Axis defeat, at the Battle of Kursk, crippled German offensive
capabilities permanently and cleared the way for Soviet offensives.
Several Axis allies defected to the Allies, such as Italy, Romania and Bulgaria.
The Eastern Front concluded with the capture of Berlin, followed by the signing of the German
Instrument of Surrender on 8 May, ending the Eastern Front and the war in Europe.
The battles on the Eastern Front constituted the
largest military confrontation in history.
In pursuit of its "Lebensraum" settler-colonial agenda, Nazi Germany waged a war
of annihilation (Vernichtungskrieg) throughout Eastern Europe.
Nazi military operations were characterised by brutality, scorched earth tactics, wanton
destruction, mass deportations, starvation, wholesale terrorism, and massacres.
These included the genocidal campaigns of Generalplan Ost and the Hunger Plan, which sought the
extermination and ethnic cleansing of more than a hundred million Eastern Europeans.
German historian Ernst Nolte called the Eastern Front "the most atrocious war of conquest, enslavement, and annihilation known to modern history", while British historian Robin
Cross expressed that "In the Second World War no theatre was more gruelling and destructive than the Eastern Front, and nowhere was the fighting more bitter".
The two principal belligerent powers in the Eastern Front were Germany
and the Soviet Union, along with their respective allies.
Though they never sent ground troops to the Eastern Front, the United States and the United Kingdom both provided
substantial material aid to the Soviet Union in the form of the Lend-Lease program, along with naval and air support.
The joint German–Finnish operations across the northernmost Finnish–Soviet border
and in the Murmansk region are considered part of the Eastern Front.
In addition, the Soviet–Finnish Continuation War is generally also
considered the northern flank of the Eastern Front.